

Curriculum Vitae for Mats K. Brun

Personal information

Address: Uelands gate 57M E-mail: mats@xal.no

0457 Oslo Phone: +47 908 00 174

Born: 19.04.1988 Nationality: Norwegian

Summary

I hold a PhD in Applied and Computational Mathematics, and have several years of experience with mathematical modeling and scientific programming. Through my work as a researcher both at the University of Bergen and at the University of Oslo, I have gained a good understanding of mathematical modeling and numerical simulation of diverse real-world systems, ranging from geothermal energy storage to evolutionary biology.

Technical skills

Frameworks NumPy, SciPy, FEniCS, Pandas, MatPlotLib, Keras

Languages Python, Java, MatLab, Haskell

Numerical (Mixed) Finite Element Method, Finite Volume Method

methods

Tools Git, LATEX, Microsoft Office

Education

2012 BSc in Physics, Department of Physics and Technology, University of

Bergen

2013 - 2015 MSc in Applid and Computational Mathematics, Department of

Mathematics, University of Bergen. Thesis title: 'Wave breaking in

long wave models and undular bores'

2016 – 2019 PhD in Applied and Computational Mathematics, Department of

Mathematics, University of Bergen. Thesis title: 'Upscaling, analysis, and iterative numerical solution schemes for thermo-poroelasticity'. Main supervisor: Florin Radu. Co-supervisors: Inga Berre and Jan M.

Nordbotten

Professional experience

2008 - 2011	Part-time employee at Dolly Dimple's Torgallmenningen, Bergen
2014	Teaching assistant in Calculus II (MAT112) at the University of Bergen
2011 - 2016	Part-time Team Leader at ADAM 2326
2016	Substitute teacher (with varying hours) in mathematics and physics
	at Bergen Katedralskole
2016 - 2019	PhD Research Fellow aff. with the Porous Media Group, Department
	of Mathematics, University of Bergen
2018	Visiting researcher, Institute of Applied Mathematics, Leibniz Univer-
	sität Hannover, Germany
2019	Co-supervisor for a MSc student aff. with the Porous Media Group
2019	Analyst at Frende Insurance, Bergen
2020 - 2021	Postdoctoral Fellow at CEES - Centre for Ecological and Evolutionary
	Synthesis, Department of Biosciences, University of Oslo
2021	Part-time position (20%) as teacher in mathematics (S2) at Sonans,
	Oslo
2021 –	IT-Consultant at Expert Analytics

Languages

English Fluent (written and spoken)

Norwegian Native language

Personal skills

Analytical Through many years of technical education I have gained a good abi-

lity to think logically and analytically, and am not afraid to confront

challenging problems.

Communication Several teaching experiences both at the high-school and university leand teaching

vels has augmented my ability to internalize and communicate difficult

concepts.

Creative Extensive experience in creative thinking, both in terms of creative

solutions to academic and technical problems, and in terms of music

performance and production.

Modeling and Extensive experience with mathematical modeling of real-world sysscientific tems, and design and implementation of numerical algorithms.

programming

Problem Always up for a new challenge, and always eager to learn new skills

solving and explore new technology.

Some interests and hobbies

Music Guitar, Piano, Music production

Personal Personal development, Traveling, Live music, Reading

Sports Weightlifting, Running, Hiking, Skiing

Extended descriptions of selected projects

Activity Drivers of evolutionary change: Understanding stasis and non-stasis

through integration of micro- and macroevolution

Period 2020 – 2021
Role Researcher
Staffing Team of 4
Volume Full-time

Description As a postdoctoral researcher in biomathematics, I was part of a re-

search team led by Prof. Nils Chr. Stenseth and Prof. Jan Martin Nordbotten, devoted to developing a mathematical framework for ecoevolutionary modeling. In particular, to connect evolutionary models at different scales in a unified mathematical framework. E.g., one may consider a population as a system of interacting species, or, one may consider the population as distinct individuals without imposing the category of species upon them. A multi-scale description of an ecoevolutionary system can therefore give new insight into phenomena such as speciation. My role in this project was two-fold: To extend the existing mathematical framework in a more mathematically rigorous direction, and to apply this framework to a real-world eco-evolutionary

system using biological data.

Tools Mathematical modeling and analysis, Mathematical biology, Finite Vo-

lume Method, MatLab, Latex

Activity An iterative staggered scheme for phase field brittle fracture propaga-

tion with stabilizing parameters

Period 2018
Role Researcher
Staffing Team of 5
Volume Full-time

Description During my doctoral work I spent some time at the Leibniz Universität

Hannover, Germany, as a visiting researcher, where I collaborated with Prof. Thomas Wick. The purpose of this collaboration was to work on numerical solution algorithms for fracture propagation in brittle materials, where the fracture surface is represented by a phase-field variable. Our strategy was to decouple the mechanics from the phase-field and solve each linearized subproblem separately, while iteratively updating coupling terms. Analysis of the proposed algorithm revealed bounds on the elastic strain and the thickness of the phase-field surface for which convergence is guaranteed. Moreover, stabilizing parameters were introduced and tailored specifically to each subproblem. The resulting algorithm is a stable and efficient solution procedure for the notoriously difficult phase-field brittle fracture propagation problems,

including conditions for guaranteed convergence.

Tools Mechanics, Finite Element Method, Latyex, Deal II

Activity Upscaling, analysis, and iterative numerical solution schemes for

thermo-poroelasticity

Period 2016 - 2019Role Researcher Staffing Team of 5 Volume Full-time

Description The main objectives of my doctoral research was to provide part of

the mathematical models and simulation technology required to assess large-scale deployment of thermo-mechanical subsurface energy storage in the context of intermittent renewable energy. The relevant physical processes for this application is the coupling of geomechenics, flow, and heat transfer within a porous material, i.e., thermoporoelasticity. Thus, together with my supervisors; Prof. Florin Radu, Prof. Inga Berre, and Prof. Jan Martin Nordbotten, we focused on different aspects of thermo-poroelasticity, relevant for the previously mentioned application, and under the technical umbrella of mathematical modeling and analysis. In particular, the research was separated into three parts; (1) modeling, (2) analysis, and (3) implementation.

Tools Mathematical modeling and analysis, Finite Element Method, Python,

Numpy, SciPy, Latex

Publications

Journal Computers & Mathematics with Applications

Date 2020

Authors Brun, Mats Kirkesæther and Ahmed, Elyes and Berre, Inga and Nord-

botten, Jan Martin and Radu, Florin Adrian

Title Monolithic and splitting solution schemes for fully coupled quasi-static

thermo-poroelasticity with nonlinear convective transport

Summary This paper concerns monolithic and splitting-based iterative proce-

dures for the coupled nonlinear thermo-poroelasticity model problem. The thermo-poroelastic model problem we consider is formulated as a three-field system of PDE's, consisting of an energy balance equation, a mass balance equation and a momentum balance equation, where the primary variables are temperature, fluid pressure, and elastic displacement. Due to the presence of a nonlinear convective transport term in the energy balance equation, it is convenient to have access to both the pressure and temperature gradients. Hence, we introduce these as two additional variables and extend the original three-field model to a five-field model. For the numerical solution of this five-field formulation, we compare six approaches that differ by how we treat the coupling/decoupling between the flow and/from heat and/from the mechanics, suitable for varying coupling strength between the three physical processes. We provide a convergence proof for the derived algorithms, and demonstrate their performance through several numerical examples investigating different strengths of the coupling

between the different processes.

DOL https://doi.org/10.1016/j.camwa.2020.08.022 Journal Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering

Date 2020

Authors Brun, Mats Kirkesæther and Wick, Thomas and Berre, Inga and Nord-

botten, Jan Martin and Radu, Florin Adrian

Title An iterative staggered scheme for phase field brittle fracture propaga-

tion with stabilizing parameters

Summary This paper concerns the analysis and implementation of a novel ite-

rative staggered scheme for quasi-static brittle fracture propagation models, where the fracture evolution is tracked by a phase field variable. The model we consider is a two-field variational inequality system, with the phase field function and the elastic displacements of the solid material as independent variables. Using a penalization strategy, this variational inequality system is transformed into a variational equality system, which is the formulation we take as the starting point for our algorithmic developments. The proposed scheme involves a partitioning of this model into two subproblems; phase field and mechanics, with added stabilization terms to both subproblems for improved efficiency and robustness. We analyze the convergence of the proposed scheme using a fixed point argument, and find that under a natural condition, the elastic mechanical energy remains bounded, and, if the diffusive zone around crack surfaces is sufficiently thick, monotonic convergence is achieved. Finally, the proposed scheme is validated numerically with several bench-mark problems.

DOI https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cma.2019.112752

Journal Journal of Mathematical Analysis and Applications

Date 2019

Authors Brun, Mats Kirkesæther and Ahmed, Elyes and Nordbotten, Jan Mar-

tin and Radu, Florin Adrian

Title Well-posedness of the fully coupled quasi-static thermo-poroelastic

equations with nonlinear convective transport

Summary This paper is concerned with the analysis of the quasi-static thermo-

poroelastic model. This model is nonlinear and includes thermal effects compared to the classical quasi-static poroelastic model (also known as Biot's model). It consists of a momentum balance equation, a mass balance equation, and an energy balance equation, fully coupled and nonlinear due to a convective transport term in the energy balance equation. The aim of this article is to investigate, in the context of mixed formulations, the existence and uniqueness of a weak solution to this model problem. The primary variables in these formulations are the fluid pressure, temperature and elastic displacement as well as the Darcy flux, heat flux and total stress. The well-posedness of a linearized formulation is addressed first through the use of a Galerkin method and suitable a priori estimates. This is used next to study the well-posedness of an iterative solution procedure for the full nonlinear problem. A convergence proof for this algorithm is then inferred by a contraction of successive difference functions of the iterates using

suitable norms.

DOI https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmaa.2018.10.074